<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI
    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Metrical Summaries</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>New electronic edition.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>New edition edited from photography of Venetus A manuscript.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div
                n="9"
                type="book">
                
                <div n="385" type="poem">
                    <l n="1">Alpha contains prayers of Chrysēs; plague among the army; enmity of the leaders</l>
                    <l n="2">And Beta has a dream, an assembly, and enumerates the ships.</l>
                    <l n="3">And then Gamma is from the point of view of Helen; the pitch of battle is only for husbands.</l>
                    <l n="4">Delta contains an assembly of the gods, many oaths, the onslaught of Ares.</l>
                    <l n="5">“E”: The son of Tydeus strikes Aphrodite and Ares.</l>
                    <l n="6">And then Zeta is the fond discourse of both Andromache and Hektor.</l>
                    <l n="7">And Eta: Aias fights one-on-one with radiant Hektor.</l>
                    <l n="8">Theta is an assembly of the gods, the power of the Trojans, the boast of Hektor.</l>
                    <l n="9">And an embassy to implacable Achilleus, is Iota.</l>
                    <l n="10">And Kappa: men from both sides went forth to spy.</l>
                    <l n="11">And Lambda. Men of Hektor strike the best of the Danaans.</l>
                    <l n="12">Mu. By the hands of the Trojans, the Achaians’ wall is hurled down.</l>
                    <l n="13">And Nu. Poseidon gives power to the Danaans in secret.</l>
                    <l n="14">Xi. Hera beguiles the Son of Kronos by sleep and the pleasures of the couch.</l>
                    <l n="15">“O”. The Son of Kronos is angered at Poseidon and Hera.</l>
                    <l n="16">Pi. Hektor’s spear kills warlike Patroklos.</l>
                    <l n="17">Rho. The Danaans and Trojans clash over the corpse.</l>
                    <l n="18">Sigma. Thetis brings arms from Hephaestus for Achilleus.</l>
                    <l n="19">And Tau. Radiant Achilleus sets aside anger and springs forth.</l>
                    <l n="20">“U”. Strife arises among the gods and brings strength to the Achaeans.</l>
                    <l n="21">Phi. By an even greater downpouring, Achilleus overcomes the Trojans.</l>
                    <l n="22">Chi. And leading him around the walls three times, Achilleus kills Hektor.</l>
                    <l n="23">Psi. Achilleus completes giving games for the Danaans.</l>
                    <l n="24">“Ō”. Achilleus, having taken a ransom, gives Priam the corpse of his son.</l>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
